<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Passkeys on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/passkeys/</link><description>Recent content in Passkeys on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 12:18:32 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/passkeys/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Implement Passkey Authentication with Go - WebAuthn Tutorial</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/11/how-to-implement-passkey-authentication-go-webauthn.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 12:18:32 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/11/how-to-implement-passkey-authentication-go-webauthn.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Passwords are broken. I spent three months building a user authentication system with email verification, password reset flows, and security best practices. Within the first month, we dealt with credential stuffing attacks, phishing complaints, and a flood of &amp;ldquo;forgot password&amp;rdquo; support tickets. Then I implemented passkey authentication and everything changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passkeys are changing how we think about web authentication. Built on the WebAuthn standard and FIDO2 protocol, they eliminate passwords entirely by using public-key cryptography. Users authenticate with biometrics, device PINs, or security keys instead of remembering passwords. Google, Apple, Microsoft, and major platforms have adopted passkeys, and more users are switching every day.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What Are Passkeys? How to Enable Them on Google, Apple, and Password Managers (2025 Guide)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/what-are-passkeys-how-to-enable-google-apple-password-managers.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/what-are-passkeys-how-to-enable-google-apple-password-managers.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Passkeys are increasingly supported across major platforms. They enable fast, convenient logins without passwords and are resistant to phishing. No more weak passwords or OTP codes hijacked via SIM swaps. This guide explains how passkeys work, compares them with legacy 2FA, and shows how to enable them on Google and Apple or use them with password managers like 1Password and Bitwarden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="summary-what-is-a-passkey"&gt;Summary: What Is a Passkey?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A passkey is a passwordless credential based on FIDO2/WebAuthn. Instead of typing a shared secret, you prove possession of a private cryptographic key securely stored on your device (or in a compatible password manager). When you log in, the site/app sends a challenge that only your private key can sign. The server verifies the signature with the public key you registered. No shared secret travels over the network.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>