<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Security on Buana Coding</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/security/</link><description>Recent content in Security on Buana Coding</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 17:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Phishing: Signs, Fake Email Examples, and How to Avoid Them (2025 Guide)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/phishing-signs-fake-email-examples-how-to-avoid.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/phishing-signs-fake-email-examples-how-to-avoid.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Staying safe online is getting harder. Scammers use convincing emails, text messages, websites, and even mobile apps to trick people into giving away passwords, banking details, or installing malware. This plain-English guide explains the most common phishing signs, shows realistic (safe) examples, and gives you clear steps to protect yourself.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-phishing">What Is Phishing?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Phishing is a social-engineering attack where criminals pretend to be a trusted brand, coworker, or service (bank, delivery company, marketplace, government agency) to make you click a link, open a file, or share sensitive information. Modern phishing blends good design with urgency (“Your account will be closed in 24 hours!”) so you act before thinking.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>FastAPI JWT Auth with OAuth2 Password Flow (Pydantic v2 + SQLAlchemy 2.0)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/fastapi-jwt-auth-oauth2-password-flow-pydantic-v2-sqlalchemy-2.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 07:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/fastapi-jwt-auth-oauth2-password-flow-pydantic-v2-sqlalchemy-2.html</guid><description>&lt;p>Looking to add login to your FastAPI app without pulling in a full auth service? Here’s a small, production‑friendly setup. We’ll build username/password authentication with the OAuth2 Password flow and JSON Web Tokens (JWTs) for stateless access. It uses Pydantic v2 for validation and SQLAlchemy 2.0 for persistence. You’ll hash passwords properly, create/verify tokens, protect routes, and test everything end‑to‑end.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you’re deploying the finished app on Ubuntu with HTTPS, check the deployment guide: &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/deploy-fastapi-ubuntu-24-04-gunicorn-nginx-certbot.html">
 Deploy FastAPI on Ubuntu 24.04: Gunicorn + Nginx + Certbot
&lt;/a>
.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Stop Reusing Passwords: A Practical Guide to Password Managers</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/stop-reusing-passwords-practical-password-manager-guide.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 01:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/stop-reusing-passwords-practical-password-manager-guide.html</guid><description>&lt;p>If you reuse passwords, the internet is quietly stacking odds against you. One small site gets breached, your email and password leak, and attackers try the same combo on your email, banking, cloud storage—everywhere. That “I’ll remember it” system works right up until it doesn’t. The fix isn’t superhuman memory; it’s outsourcing the problem to a tool designed for it: a password manager.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What a password manager actually does&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Generates strong, unique passwords for every account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stores them encrypted, synced across your devices&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Auto‑fills only on the correct websites/apps&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Audits your vault for weak/reused/compromised passwords&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Holds secure notes, TOTP codes (in some apps), and sometimes passkeys&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The goal is simple: every account gets its own high‑entropy secret, and you never type or remember it again.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>