<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Web Development on Buana Coding</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/web-development/</link><description>Recent content in Web Development on Buana Coding</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 02:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/web-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>GraphQL with Golang - A Modern Alternative to REST API</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/graphql-golang-modern-alternative-rest-api.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 02:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/graphql-golang-modern-alternative-rest-api.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The landscape of API development has evolved significantly over the past decade. While REST APIs have been the dominant architecture for building web services, GraphQL has emerged as a compelling alternative that addresses many limitations of traditional REST-based approaches. When combined with Go&amp;rsquo;s performance and simplicity, GraphQL creates a powerful foundation for modern API development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-graphql-beyond-traditional-rest"&gt;Understanding GraphQL: Beyond Traditional REST&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GraphQL represents a paradigm shift in how we think about API design and data fetching. Unlike REST, which exposes multiple endpoints for different resources, GraphQL provides a single endpoint that can handle complex queries with precise data requirements.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Building REST API with Gin Framework Golang - Production Ready</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/building-rest-api-gin-framework-golang-production-ready.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 02:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/building-rest-api-gin-framework-golang-production-ready.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building a REST API might seem straightforward at first glance, but creating one that&amp;rsquo;s actually ready for production is a different beast entirely. After spending years working with various Go frameworks, I can tell you that the Gin framework hits that sweet spot between developer productivity and performance that makes it perfect for building robust APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been building &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/05/how-to-build-a-rest-api-in-go-using-net-http.html"&gt;
 basic REST APIs with Go&amp;rsquo;s net/http package
&lt;/a&gt;
, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably noticed how much boilerplate code you need to write for routing, middleware, and request handling. That&amp;rsquo;s where Gin shines - it provides all the essential features you need while maintaining the performance advantages that make Go special.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>10 Essential VS Code Extensions Every Developer Must Have in 2025</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/10-essential-vscode-extensions-developers-2025.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/10-essential-vscode-extensions-developers-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s be honest – vanilla Visual Studio Code is good, but it&amp;rsquo;s not &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;. What makes this popular code editor truly shine are the extensions that turn it into a powerhouse IDE. After years of coding and trying countless extensions, I&amp;rsquo;ve narrowed down the absolute essentials that every developer should have installed in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;rsquo;re a seasoned developer or just starting your coding journey, these extensions will save you hours of work, catch bugs before they happen, and make your coding experience so much smoother. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into the tools that have become indispensable in modern development.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>