<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Developer Tools on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/developer-tools/</link><description>Recent content in Developer Tools on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 09:18:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/developer-tools/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Modern CLI Tools That Replace the Classics (grep, cat, ls, find, and More)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2026/02/modern-cli-tools-that-replace-the-classics.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 09:18:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2026/02/modern-cli-tools-that-replace-the-classics.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Most developers spend hours every day in the terminal. And most of us are still using tools written in the 1970s and 80s — &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cat&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;find&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;. They work, sure. But they were designed for a time when terminals had 24 rows and 80 columns, file systems were tiny, and nobody expected colored output or Unicode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime in the last few years, people started building modern replacements. Mostly in Rust, some in Go. They&amp;rsquo;re faster, they have sane defaults, and they produce output you can actually read without squinting. I&amp;rsquo;ve been swapping out the classics one by one, and at this point I can&amp;rsquo;t go back.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What Is Vibe Coding? How Developers Actually Build Software with AI in 2026</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2026/02/what-is-vibe-coding-ai-powered-development-guide.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 09:07:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2026/02/what-is-vibe-coding-ai-powered-development-guide.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been on tech Twitter, Reddit, or any developer forum in the past year, you&amp;rsquo;ve seen the term &lt;strong&gt;vibe coding&lt;/strong&gt; thrown around constantly. Some people swear by it. Others think it&amp;rsquo;s the beginning of the end for &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; programming. And a lot of developers are quietly using it every day without making a big deal about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the last several months going deep into vibe coding workflows, and I want to share what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned: what it actually is, where it works well, where it completely falls apart, and what this all means if you write code for a living.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>10 Best AI Coding Assistants Every Developer Should Try in 2025</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/10-best-ai-coding-assistants-every-developer-should-try-2025.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 15:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/10-best-ai-coding-assistants-every-developer-should-try-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The way we write code is changing dramatically. AI coding assistants have moved from experimental tools to essential companions that can genuinely transform your development workflow. I&amp;rsquo;ve been testing AI coding tools since they first emerged, and honestly, the progress in 2025 has been mind-blowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What used to take hours of debugging, researching documentation, or writing boilerplate code can now be done in minutes. But with so many AI coding assistants flooding the market, choosing the right one feels overwhelming. That&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;ve spent months testing every major AI coding tool to bring you this comprehensive guide.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Essential Linux Commands Every Developer Must Know in 2025</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/essential-linux-commands-every-developer-must-know-2025.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/essential-linux-commands-every-developer-must-know-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;rsquo;re building web applications, managing servers, or working in DevOps, mastering Linux commands is absolutely essential for any developer in 2025. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with Linux systems for years, and I can tell you that knowing the right commands at the right time can save you hours of work and make you incredibly productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux dominates the server world, powers most cloud infrastructure, and is the backbone of modern development environments. From managing &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/install-docker-on-ubuntu-24-04-with-compose-v2-and-rootless.html"&gt;
 Docker containers
&lt;/a&gt;
 to setting up &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/nginx-certbot-ubuntu-24-04-free-https.html"&gt;
 secure web servers with HTTPS
&lt;/a&gt;
, these commands will be your daily companions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>10 Essential VS Code Extensions Every Developer Must Have in 2025</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/10-essential-vscode-extensions-developers-2025.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/10-essential-vscode-extensions-developers-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s be honest &amp;ndash; vanilla Visual Studio Code is good, but it&amp;rsquo;s not &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;. What makes this popular code editor truly shine are the extensions that turn it into a powerhouse IDE. After years of coding and trying countless extensions, I&amp;rsquo;ve narrowed down the absolute essentials that every developer should have installed in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;rsquo;re a seasoned developer or just starting your coding journey, these extensions will save you hours of work, catch bugs before they happen, and make your coding experience so much smoother. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into the tools that have become indispensable in modern development.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>