<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Logging on Buana Coding</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/logging/</link><description>Recent content in Logging on Buana Coding</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/logging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Advanced Laravel Debugging with Logs Production Issues Troubleshooting</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/advanced-laravel-debugging-with-logs.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/advanced-laravel-debugging-with-logs.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When your Laravel application starts acting up in production, proper logging becomes your lifeline. Unlike development environments where you can use tools like dd() or dump(), production debugging requires a more sophisticated approach. This comprehensive guide walks you through advanced Laravel debugging techniques using logs that will help you identify, track, and resolve production issues efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-laravels-logging-architecture"&gt;Understanding Laravel&amp;rsquo;s Logging Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laravel provides a robust logging system built on top of the Monolog library. The framework offers multiple logging channels, each designed for specific use cases. Before diving into advanced debugging techniques, you need to understand how Laravel handles logging under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Complete Guide to slog (Go 1.21+) Modern Structured Logging in Go (2025)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/complete-guide-slog-go-structured-logging-2025.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/complete-guide-slog-go-structured-logging-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Go 1.21 introduced &lt;code&gt;log/slog&lt;/code&gt;, a standard structured logging API that finally brings first‑class JSON and attribute‑based logging to the standard library. If you’ve used &lt;code&gt;zap&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;logrus&lt;/code&gt;, the core ideas will feel familiar&amp;ndash;just simpler and standardized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide takes you from zero to production-ready logging with &lt;code&gt;slog&lt;/code&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll start with basic setup, then gradually build up to advanced patterns like HTTP middleware, security, testing, and observability integration. Each section includes working examples you can run immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>