<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Production on Buana Coding</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/production/</link><description>Recent content in Production on Buana Coding</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 06:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/production/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Containerize and Deploy Go Apps with Docker</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-containerize-and-deploy-go-apps-with-docker.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 06:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-containerize-and-deploy-go-apps-with-docker.html</guid><description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deploying Go applications used to mean SSH into servers, copying binaries, managing dependencies, and praying everything works. Different machines had different library versions. Production behaved differently than development. Debugging deployment issues wasted hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Docker for Go?&lt;/strong&gt; Docker is a containerization platform that packages your Go application and all its dependencies into a portable container image. Instead of installing Go and dependencies on every server, Docker bundles everything your app needs into a container that runs identically everywhere - from your laptop to production servers.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Building REST API with Gin Framework Golang - Production Ready</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/building-rest-api-gin-framework-golang-production-ready.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 02:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/building-rest-api-gin-framework-golang-production-ready.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building a REST API might seem straightforward at first glance, but creating one that&amp;rsquo;s actually ready for production is a different beast entirely. After spending years working with various Go frameworks, I can tell you that the Gin framework hits that sweet spot between developer productivity and performance that makes it perfect for building robust APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been building &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/05/how-to-build-a-rest-api-in-go-using-net-http.html"&gt;
 basic REST APIs with Go&amp;rsquo;s net/http package
&lt;/a&gt;
, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably noticed how much boilerplate code you need to write for routing, middleware, and request handling. That&amp;rsquo;s where Gin shines - it provides all the essential features you need while maintaining the performance advantages that make Go special.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Error Tracking Tools and Techniques</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-production-monitoring-error-tracking.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-production-monitoring-error-tracking.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Running a Laravel application in production without proper monitoring is like driving blindfolded - you won&amp;rsquo;t know there&amp;rsquo;s a problem until you crash. The moment your app goes live, dozens of things can go wrong: database connections can fail, APIs can timeout, memory can run out, or users might trigger unexpected errors you never saw during development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good monitoring isn&amp;rsquo;t just about knowing when things break - it&amp;rsquo;s about catching issues before they affect users, understanding performance trends, and having the data you need to fix problems quickly. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re running a small business site or a high-traffic application, the right monitoring setup can save you countless sleepless nights and frustrated customer calls.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Development and Production Environment Setup</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-docker-setup-development-production.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 07:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-docker-setup-development-production.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Docker makes Laravel environments consistent across machines and stages. The steps below outline a clean setup for local development and a hardened build for production. Run PHP‑FPM behind Nginx, connect to MySQL/Postgres and Redis, toggle Xdebug when needed, and ship a small, cache‑friendly image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="components"&gt;Components&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHP‑FPM container for the application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nginx container as the HTTP entry point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL or Postgres, plus Redis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;code&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; for development with bind mounts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A multi‑stage Dockerfile for a compact production image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="project-layout"&gt;Project layout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-text" data-lang="text"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;app/ # your Laravel app code
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;docker/
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; nginx/
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; default.conf
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;Dockerfile
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;docker-compose.yml
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id="dockerfile-multistage"&gt;Dockerfile (multi‑stage)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Build dependencies once, then copy only what you need into the runtime image. Enable OPcache for production; allow an Xdebug toggle for local work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fix Laravel Permission Issues Solving 403 and 500 Errors on Production Server</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fix-laravel-permission-issues-production.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fix-laravel-permission-issues-production.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If a fresh deploy returns 403 or 500, the cause is usually predictable: wrong ownership/permissions, web server misconfig, missing PHP extensions, or SELinux. Use the checklist below to find and fix it quickly. Examples cover Ubuntu/Debian (Nginx/Apache with PHP‑FPM) and CentOS/RHEL (SELinux).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-403-vs-500"&gt;Why 403 vs 500&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;403 Forbidden from the web server: The server blocked access before Laravel ran. Common causes: wrong document root (not pointing to &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt;), missing &lt;code&gt;try_files&lt;/code&gt;, directory or file not readable, SELinux contexts, or a security module (WAF/mod_security/Cloudflare) rejecting the request.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;403 from Laravel: Authorization middleware/policies, CSRF token failures, or custom gates deny the action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;500 Internal Server Error: PHP crashed or threw an exception. Common causes: wrong permissions on &lt;code&gt;storage/&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;bootstrap/cache&lt;/code&gt;, missing PHP extensions, invalid &lt;code&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt;, wrong &lt;code&gt;APP_KEY&lt;/code&gt;, or syntax/runtime errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="quick-fix-checklist-safe-defaults"&gt;Quick fix checklist (safe defaults)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run these commands from your project root (adjust the PHP‑FPM user for your distro):&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Complete Production Security Guide</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-security-best-practices-production.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 12:15:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-security-best-practices-production.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Security is paramount when deploying Laravel applications to production environments. A single vulnerability can compromise user data, damage your reputation, and result in significant financial losses. This comprehensive guide covers essential security practices to protect your Laravel applications from common threats and vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laravel provides excellent security features out of the box, but proper implementation and additional security measures are crucial for production deployments. From authentication and authorization to data protection and server hardening, every layer of your application stack requires careful attention to security details.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Complete Guide to slog (Go 1.21+) Modern Structured Logging in Go (2025)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/complete-guide-slog-go-structured-logging-2025.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/complete-guide-slog-go-structured-logging-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Go 1.21 introduced &lt;code&gt;log/slog&lt;/code&gt;, a standard structured logging API that finally brings first‑class JSON and attribute‑based logging to the standard library. If you’ve used &lt;code&gt;zap&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;logrus&lt;/code&gt;, the core ideas will feel familiar—just simpler and standardized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide takes you from zero to production-ready logging with &lt;code&gt;slog&lt;/code&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll start with basic setup, then gradually build up to advanced patterns like HTTP middleware, security, testing, and observability integration. Each section includes working examples you can run immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>