<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>CLI on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/cli/</link><description>Recent content in CLI on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 09:18:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/cli/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Modern CLI Tools That Replace the Classics (grep, cat, ls, find, and More)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2026/02/modern-cli-tools-that-replace-the-classics.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2026 09:18:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2026/02/modern-cli-tools-that-replace-the-classics.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Most developers spend hours every day in the terminal. And most of us are still using tools written in the 1970s and 80s — &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cat&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;find&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;. They work, sure. But they were designed for a time when terminals had 24 rows and 80 columns, file systems were tiny, and nobody expected colored output or Unicode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime in the last few years, people started building modern replacements. Mostly in Rust, some in Go. They&amp;rsquo;re faster, they have sane defaults, and they produce output you can actually read without squinting. I&amp;rsquo;ve been swapping out the classics one by one, and at this point I can&amp;rsquo;t go back.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Build a CLI Tool in Go with Cobra and Viper</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-build-a-cli-tool-in-go-with-cobra-and-viper.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 14:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-build-a-cli-tool-in-go-with-cobra-and-viper.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve built a lot of CLI tools over the years - deployment scripts, database migration tools, log analyzers, you name it. Every time I start a new one, I reach for Cobra and Viper. Not because they&amp;rsquo;re trendy (though they are), but because they solve the boring parts so I can focus on what my tool actually does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about kubectl, hugo, gh (GitHub CLI) - all built with Cobra. There&amp;rsquo;s a reason for that. Cobra gives you a clean command structure, automatic help generation, flag parsing, and all the stuff you&amp;rsquo;d otherwise spend hours implementing. Viper adds configuration management so users can configure your tool however they want - config files, environment variables, flags, whatever.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>