<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cache on Buana Coding</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/cache/</link><description>Recent content in Cache on Buana Coding</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 12:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/cache/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Fixing Laravel Session and Cache Issues: Complete Troubleshooting Guide</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fixing-laravel-session-cache-issues.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 12:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fixing-laravel-session-cache-issues.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sessions and cache power many core features in Laravel—from authentication to performance. When they break, symptoms can be confusing: users get logged out randomly, “remember me” does nothing, flash messages disappear, or recent cache writes don’t show up. Use the checklist below to quickly find and fix the cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-sessions-and-cache-fail"&gt;How sessions and cache fail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sessions persist state across requests. Laravel can store them in files, database, Redis, Memcached, or array (for tests). If the storage can’t be written or the cookie can’t be read back, the user appears “logged out”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cache stores computed data for speed. If the driver points to a different backend than you expect, or the key gets namespaced differently, you’ll read stale or missing values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="quick-fixes-that-solve-most-cases"&gt;Quick fixes that solve most cases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run these from your app root (adjust user/group):&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel Environment Configuration: Fixing .env and Config Cache Issues</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-environment-configuration-env-issues.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-environment-configuration-env-issues.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Env problems often show up right after a deploy or a cache command: the app works locally but fails in production with “No application encryption key has been specified”, wrong database credentials, missing API keys, or stale config even after you edited &lt;code&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt;. This happens because of how Laravel loads environment variables and how config caching freezes values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-laravel-reads-environment-variables"&gt;How Laravel reads environment variables&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laravel reads environment variables in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>