<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>REST API on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/rest-api/</link><description>Recent content in REST API on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 08:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/rest-api/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Build a REST API with Django REST Framework (Production Ready)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-build-rest-api-django-rest-framework-production-ready.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 08:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-build-rest-api-django-rest-framework-production-ready.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I still remember the first time I built an API for a client&amp;rsquo;s e-commerce platform. I chose FastAPI because everyone on Twitter was hyping it up&amp;ndash;&amp;ldquo;blazing fast,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;modern Python,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;async everything.&amp;rdquo; The initial setup was smooth, and I built endpoints quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then reality hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The client needed a complex admin panel to manage products, orders, and users. They wanted role-based permissions with granular controls. They needed integration with their existing Django authentication system. And oh, they wanted detailed audit logs for every database change.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Implement Rate Limiting in Go - Protect Your API from Abuse</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-implement-rate-limiting-in-go-protect-api-from-abuse.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-implement-rate-limiting-in-go-protect-api-from-abuse.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;APIs power modern applications by exposing functionality to clients, but unrestricted access creates vulnerabilities. A single misbehaving client can overwhelm your server, degrading performance for all users. Malicious actors can exploit unprotected endpoints to scrape data, attempt credential stuffing, or launch denial of service attacks. Rate limiting provides the first line of defense against these threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This comprehensive guide demonstrates how to implement rate limiting in Go applications. You&amp;rsquo;ll learn multiple algorithms including token bucket and sliding window approaches, build middleware for automatic request throttling, implement per-IP and per-user limiting strategies, integrate Redis for distributed systems, and follow production best practices for protecting your APIs effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Implement JWT Authentication in Go - Secure REST API Tutorial</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/how-to-implement-jwt-authentication-in-go-secure-rest-api.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 09:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/how-to-implement-jwt-authentication-in-go-secure-rest-api.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Authentication sits at the foundation of any secure application. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re building a REST API, microservice, or full-stack web application, you need a reliable way to verify user identity and protect sensitive endpoints. JWT (JSON Web Token) has become the de facto standard for stateless authentication in modern applications, and Go provides excellent tools for implementing it correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide walks through implementing JWT authentication in Go from the ground up. You&amp;rsquo;ll learn how to generate tokens, validate them, handle refresh tokens, create authentication middleware, and follow security best practices that work in production environments. By the end, you&amp;rsquo;ll have a complete authentication system ready to integrate into your Go applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Building REST API with Gin Framework Golang - Production Ready</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/building-rest-api-gin-framework-golang-production-ready.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 02:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/building-rest-api-gin-framework-golang-production-ready.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building a REST API might seem straightforward at first glance, but creating one that&amp;rsquo;s actually ready for production is a different beast entirely. After spending years working with various Go frameworks, I can tell you that the Gin framework hits that sweet spot between developer productivity and performance that makes it perfect for building robust APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been building &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/05/how-to-build-a-rest-api-in-go-using-net-http.html"&gt;
 basic REST APIs with Go&amp;rsquo;s net/http package
&lt;/a&gt;
, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably noticed how much boilerplate code you need to write for routing, middleware, and request handling. That&amp;rsquo;s where Gin shines - it provides all the essential features you need while maintaining the performance advantages that make Go special.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>FastAPI Tutorial Build REST API from Scratch (Beginner Guide)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/fastapi-tutorial-build-rest-api-from-scratch-beginner-guide.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 07:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/fastapi-tutorial-build-rest-api-from-scratch-beginner-guide.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building APIs used to scare me when I first started programming. There&amp;rsquo;s so much to learn - databases, HTTP methods, authentication, error handling. But FastAPI changed everything for me. It&amp;rsquo;s like having training wheels that actually make you faster, not slower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to build a real Book Library API from the ground up. No fluff, no complicated setups - just practical, working code that you can understand and expand on. By the end of this guide, you&amp;rsquo;ll have a fully functional REST API that can handle creating, reading, updating, and deleting books.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>