<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>OAuth2 on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/oauth2/</link><description>Recent content in OAuth2 on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/oauth2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Implement OAuth2 in Go Google GitHub and Facebook Login</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-implement-oauth2-in-go-google-github-facebook-login.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-implement-oauth2-in-go-google-github-facebook-login.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants to create yet another account with yet another password. I&amp;rsquo;ve built authentication systems that required users to sign up with email and password, and the drop-off rate was painful. Then I added &amp;ldquo;Login with Google&amp;rdquo; and conversions jumped 40%. Users already have accounts they trust - why make them create new ones?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OAuth2 lets users authenticate with providers they already use - Google, GitHub, Facebook, whatever. You get verified emails, users don&amp;rsquo;t manage more passwords, and everyone&amp;rsquo;s happy. The best part? It&amp;rsquo;s not as complicated as it looks once you understand the flow.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>FastAPI JWT Auth with OAuth2 Password Flow (Pydantic v2 + SQLAlchemy 2.0)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/fastapi-jwt-auth-oauth2-password-flow-pydantic-v2-sqlalchemy-2.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2025 07:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/fastapi-jwt-auth-oauth2-password-flow-pydantic-v2-sqlalchemy-2.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Looking to add login to your FastAPI app without pulling in a full auth service? Here’s a small, production‑friendly setup. We’ll build username/password authentication with the OAuth2 Password flow and JSON Web Tokens (JWTs) for stateless access. It uses Pydantic v2 for validation and SQLAlchemy 2.0 for persistence. You’ll hash passwords properly, create/verify tokens, protect routes, and test everything end‑to‑end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re deploying the finished app on Ubuntu with HTTPS, check the deployment guide: &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/deploy-fastapi-ubuntu-24-04-gunicorn-nginx-certbot.html"&gt;
 Deploy FastAPI on Ubuntu 24.04: Gunicorn + Nginx + Certbot
&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>