<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Microservices on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/microservices/</link><description>Recent content in Microservices on Level Up Your Code | Web &amp; App Development Tutorials</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/microservices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Service Discovery in Microservices Golang - Consul and etcd Implementation</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/service-discovery-microservices-golang-consul-etcd.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/service-discovery-microservices-golang-consul-etcd.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the early days of web development, finding services was simple. Your database lived at &lt;code&gt;localhost:5432&lt;/code&gt;, your cache at &lt;code&gt;localhost:6379&lt;/code&gt;, and everything was predictable. But when you move to microservices, suddenly you have dozens of services spinning up and down across multiple servers, and nobody knows where anything is anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where service discovery becomes your lifeline. Instead of hardcoding addresses and hoping for the best, you get a dynamic phone book that keeps track of who&amp;rsquo;s available, where they live, and whether they&amp;rsquo;re actually working. After building several distributed systems in Go, I can tell you that getting service discovery right is often the difference between a system that scales gracefully and one that becomes an operational nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>API Gateway with Golang - Load Balancing and Rate Limiting Implementation</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/api-gateway-golang-load-balancing-rate-limiting.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 07:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/api-gateway-golang-load-balancing-rate-limiting.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re building distributed systems, one component stands between chaos and order: the API Gateway. Think of it as the bouncer at an exclusive club - it decides who gets in, where they go, and how fast they can enter. After working with various microservice architectures, I can tell you that a well-implemented API Gateway is often the difference between a system that scales gracefully and one that crumbles under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Microservices with Golang - Architecture and Implementation Guide</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/microservices-golang-architecture-implementation-guide.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:01:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/microservices-golang-architecture-implementation-guide.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Moving from monolithic to microservices architecture has become one of the biggest changes in how we build software today. While monolithic applications bundle all functionality into a single deployable unit, microservices break down applications into smaller, independent services that communicate over well-defined APIs. When combined with Go&amp;rsquo;s performance characteristics and deployment simplicity, microservices become a powerful approach for building scalable, maintainable systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this guide, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn how to design, build, and deploy microservices using Go. We&amp;rsquo;ll cover architectural patterns, service communication strategies, containerization, and production deployment techniques that will help you build robust distributed systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Breaking Monolith into Scalable Services</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-microservices-breaking-monolith.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-microservices-breaking-monolith.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As your Laravel application grows, you might find yourself hitting the limitations of a monolithic architecture. Database bottlenecks, deployment challenges, and team coordination issues become increasingly common. The solution? Transitioning to a microservices architecture that breaks your monolith into smaller, manageable, and independently deployable services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This comprehensive guide will walk you through the entire process of decomposing your Laravel monolith into microservices, from initial planning to practical implementation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-monolith-vs-microservices"&gt;Understanding Monolith vs Microservices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A monolithic application packages all functionality into a single deployable unit. While this approach works well for small to medium applications, it presents several challenges as your application scales:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>gRPC in Go Complete Guide from Basics to Production Ready Services</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/grpc-in-go-complete-guide-from-basics-to-production.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/grpc-in-go-complete-guide-from-basics-to-production.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building modern distributed systems is tricky business - you need services that can talk to each other quickly and reliably. That&amp;rsquo;s where gRPC comes in and absolutely crushes it. I&amp;rsquo;ve been building REST APIs for years, but when I first tried gRPC, it was like switching from a bicycle to a sports car. The speed difference is insane, plus you get type safety and can use it with practically any programming language.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>