<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Performance on Buana Coding</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/performance/</link><description>Recent content in Performance on Buana Coding</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/performance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Laravel N+1 Query Problem Solution: Essential Database Optimization Guide</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-n-plus-one-query-problem-solution.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-n-plus-one-query-problem-solution.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever wondered why your Laravel app suddenly becomes sluggish when displaying lists of data, you might be dealing with the dreaded N+1 query problem. It&amp;rsquo;s one of those sneaky performance killers that can turn a fast application into a slow, resource-hungry monster. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry though - once you understand what&amp;rsquo;s happening and how to fix it, you&amp;rsquo;ll never fall into this trap again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-n1-query-problem"&gt;What is the N+1 Query Problem?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what happens: your app makes one query to get a list of records, then fires off a separate query for each record to grab related data. Picture this - you want to show 100 blog posts with their authors&amp;rsquo; names. Instead of being smart about it, your app runs one query to get the posts, then 100 more queries to fetch each author. That&amp;rsquo;s 101 database hits when you could&amp;rsquo;ve done it with just 2!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel Octane: Boost Performance with High-Speed Application Server</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-octane-boost-performance-tutorial.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-octane-boost-performance-tutorial.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re tired of waiting for your Laravel app to respond and want to see some serious speed improvements, Laravel Octane might be exactly what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for. Think of it as giving your application a turbo boost - we&amp;rsquo;re talking about performance gains that can make your app 3x to 10x faster in many scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laravel Octane takes your regular Laravel application and runs it on high-performance application servers like Swoole or RoadRunner. Instead of booting up your entire application for every single request (which is what traditional PHP does), Octane keeps your app loaded in memory and reuses it for multiple requests. The result? Lightning-fast response times that will make your users happy.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel Microservices: Breaking Monolith into Scalable Services</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-microservices-breaking-monolith.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-microservices-breaking-monolith.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As your Laravel application grows, you might find yourself hitting the limitations of a monolithic architecture. Database bottlenecks, deployment challenges, and team coordination issues become increasingly common. The solution? Transitioning to a microservices architecture that breaks your monolith into smaller, manageable, and independently deployable services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This comprehensive guide will walk you through the entire process of decomposing your Laravel monolith into microservices, from initial planning to practical implementation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-monolith-vs-microservices"&gt;Understanding Monolith vs Microservices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A monolithic application packages all functionality into a single deployable unit. While this approach works well for small to medium applications, it presents several challenges as your application scales:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel Performance Optimization: 15 Essential Techniques for Fast Applications</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-performance-optimization-15-techniques.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 12:30:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-performance-optimization-15-techniques.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Performance optimization is crucial for creating successful Laravel applications that provide excellent user experiences. Slow applications frustrate users, hurt SEO rankings, and can significantly impact business revenue. This comprehensive guide covers 15 proven techniques to dramatically improve your Laravel application&amp;rsquo;s performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern web users expect applications to load quickly and respond instantly to interactions. Studies show that even a one-second delay in page load time can reduce conversions by 7%. Laravel provides powerful tools and features to help you build fast applications, but knowing how to use them effectively makes all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>