<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Architecture on Buana Coding</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/architecture/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Architecture on Buana Coding</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 03:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Event-Driven Architecture with Golang and Message Queues</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/09/event-driven-architecture-golang-message-queues.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 03:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/09/event-driven-architecture-golang-message-queues.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditional request-response architectures work well for simple applications, but as systems grow in complexity and scale, they often become bottlenecks. Event-driven architecture gives you a better way to build systems by letting components talk to each other through messages instead of direct calls. When combined with Go&amp;rsquo;s excellent concurrency model and robust ecosystem, event-driven systems become powerful tools for building scalable, resilient applications.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this guide, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn how to build event-driven systems using Go and message queues that actually work in production. We&amp;rsquo;ll explore event sourcing patterns, CQRS implementation, and practical strategies for building systems that can handle high throughput while maintaining data consistency and system reliability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microservices with Golang - Architecture and Implementation Guide</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/09/microservices-golang-architecture-implementation-guide.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Sep 2025 00:01:00 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/09/microservices-golang-architecture-implementation-guide.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Moving from monolithic to microservices architecture has become one of the biggest changes in how we build software today. While monolithic applications bundle all functionality into a single deployable unit, microservices break down applications into smaller, independent services that communicate over well-defined APIs. When combined with Go&amp;rsquo;s performance characteristics and deployment simplicity, microservices become a powerful approach for building scalable, maintainable systems.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this guide, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn how to design, build, and deploy microservices using Go. We&amp;rsquo;ll cover architectural patterns, service communication strategies, containerization, and production deployment techniques that will help you build robust distributed systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breaking Monolith into Scalable Services</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/2025/09/laravel-microservices-breaking-monolith.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/2025/09/laravel-microservices-breaking-monolith.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As your Laravel application grows, you might find yourself hitting the limitations of a monolithic architecture. Database bottlenecks, deployment challenges, and team coordination issues become increasingly common. The solution? Transitioning to a microservices architecture that breaks your monolith into smaller, manageable, and independently deployable services.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This comprehensive guide will walk you through the entire process of decomposing your Laravel monolith into microservices, from initial planning to practical implementation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;understanding-monolith-vs-microservices&#34;&gt;Understanding Monolith vs Microservices&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A monolithic application packages all functionality into a single deployable unit. While this approach works well for small to medium applications, it presents several challenges as your application scales:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
