<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Laravel on Buana Coding</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/laravel/</link><description>Recent content in Laravel on Buana Coding</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/laravel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Laravel Database Migration Best Practices: Avoiding Fatal Mistakes</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-database-migration-best-practices.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-database-migration-best-practices.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Migrations let you evolve your schema alongside the code. Done well, they are repeatable and safe. Done poorly, they lock tables, drop data, and take your site down. This guide focuses on practical patterns that reduce risk in production and make rollouts predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ground-rules"&gt;Ground rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treat migrations as immutable once deployed. If a mistake gets to production, add a new migration to correct it instead of editing history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep schema and data changes separate. Data backfills belong in their own migration or a job/command so you can control runtime and retries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t rely on application models inside migrations. Models can drift as your app evolves. Prefer &lt;code&gt;DB::table()&lt;/code&gt; or raw SQL that doesn’t depend on future code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test locally and in staging with the same DB engine and major version you run in production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always run with &lt;code&gt;php artisan migrate --force&lt;/code&gt; in CI/production. Check status with &lt;code&gt;php artisan migrate:status&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="naming-and-versioning"&gt;Naming and versioning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use descriptive names that read like a change log: &lt;code&gt;2025_09_15_100001_add_status_to_orders_table.php&lt;/code&gt;. One concern per migration. If a change requires several steps (add column → backfill → enforce NOT NULL), use separate migrations in the right order.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel API Authentication with Sanctum: Complete Tutorial 2025</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-api-authentication-sanctum-2025.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-api-authentication-sanctum-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Laravel Sanctum offers two simple authentication modes that cover most applications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cookie-based auth for SPAs that live on the same top-level domain as your backend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal access tokens for mobile apps, third‑party clients, or server‑to‑server use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial walks through both flows end‑to‑end, including the necessary configuration (CORS, cookies, stateful domains), how to issue and revoke tokens, how to protect routes, and how to test the result. You’ll also find production notes to avoid common pitfalls.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Fix Common Laravel Errors: Complete Troubleshooting Guide for Developers</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/how-to-fix-common-laravel-errors.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/how-to-fix-common-laravel-errors.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Laravel applications fail for a handful of predictable reasons: missing or stale configuration, broken cache, database schema drift, misconfigured cookies, permissions, or plain coding mistakes. The sections below show fast, reliable ways to identify the root cause and ship a clean fix without guesswork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="start-with-a-clean-baseline"&gt;Start with a clean baseline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run these commands from the project root to eliminate stale build artifacts before you investigate further:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;php artisan cache:clear
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;php artisan config:clear
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;php artisan route:clear
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;php artisan view:clear
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;composer dump-autoload -o
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the problem is related to file permissions (very common after deploy), follow the safe defaults in this companion article: &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fix-laravel-permission-issues-production.html"&gt;
 Fix Laravel Permission Issues
&lt;/a&gt;
.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fixing Laravel Session and Cache Issues: Complete Troubleshooting Guide</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fixing-laravel-session-cache-issues.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 12:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fixing-laravel-session-cache-issues.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sessions and cache power many core features in Laravel—from authentication to performance. When they break, symptoms can be confusing: users get logged out randomly, “remember me” does nothing, flash messages disappear, or recent cache writes don’t show up. Use the checklist below to quickly find and fix the cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-sessions-and-cache-fail"&gt;How sessions and cache fail&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sessions persist state across requests. Laravel can store them in files, database, Redis, Memcached, or array (for tests). If the storage can’t be written or the cookie can’t be read back, the user appears “logged out”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cache stores computed data for speed. If the driver points to a different backend than you expect, or the key gets namespaced differently, you’ll read stale or missing values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="quick-fixes-that-solve-most-cases"&gt;Quick fixes that solve most cases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run these from your app root (adjust user/group):&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel Environment Configuration: Fixing .env and Config Cache Issues</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-environment-configuration-env-issues.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-environment-configuration-env-issues.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Env problems often show up right after a deploy or a cache command: the app works locally but fails in production with “No application encryption key has been specified”, wrong database credentials, missing API keys, or stale config even after you edited &lt;code&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt;. This happens because of how Laravel loads environment variables and how config caching freezes values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-laravel-reads-environment-variables"&gt;How Laravel reads environment variables&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laravel reads environment variables in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fix Laravel Permission Issues: Solving 403 and 500 Errors on Production Server</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fix-laravel-permission-issues-production.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 08:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/fix-laravel-permission-issues-production.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If a fresh deploy returns 403 or 500, the cause is usually predictable: wrong ownership/permissions, web server misconfig, missing PHP extensions, or SELinux. Use the checklist below to find and fix it quickly. Examples cover Ubuntu/Debian (Nginx/Apache with PHP‑FPM) and CentOS/RHEL (SELinux).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-403-vs-500"&gt;Why 403 vs 500&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;403 Forbidden from the web server: The server blocked access before Laravel ran. Common causes: wrong document root (not pointing to &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt;), missing &lt;code&gt;try_files&lt;/code&gt;, directory or file not readable, SELinux contexts, or a security module (WAF/mod_security/Cloudflare) rejecting the request.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;403 from Laravel: Authorization middleware/policies, CSRF token failures, or custom gates deny the action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;500 Internal Server Error: PHP crashed or threw an exception. Common causes: wrong permissions on &lt;code&gt;storage/&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;bootstrap/cache&lt;/code&gt;, missing PHP extensions, invalid &lt;code&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt;, wrong &lt;code&gt;APP_KEY&lt;/code&gt;, or syntax/runtime errors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="quick-fix-checklist-safe-defaults"&gt;Quick fix checklist (safe defaults)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run these commands from your project root (adjust the PHP‑FPM user for your distro):&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel Performance Optimization: 15 Essential Techniques for Fast Applications</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-performance-optimization-15-techniques.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 12:30:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-performance-optimization-15-techniques.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Performance optimization is crucial for creating successful Laravel applications that provide excellent user experiences. Slow applications frustrate users, hurt SEO rankings, and can significantly impact business revenue. This comprehensive guide covers 15 proven techniques to dramatically improve your Laravel application&amp;rsquo;s performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern web users expect applications to load quickly and respond instantly to interactions. Studies show that even a one-second delay in page load time can reduce conversions by 7%. Laravel provides powerful tools and features to help you build fast applications, but knowing how to use them effectively makes all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel Security Best Practices: Complete Production Security Guide</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-security-best-practices-production.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 12:15:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-security-best-practices-production.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Security is paramount when deploying Laravel applications to production environments. A single vulnerability can compromise user data, damage your reputation, and result in significant financial losses. This comprehensive guide covers essential security practices to protect your Laravel applications from common threats and vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laravel provides excellent security features out of the box, but proper implementation and additional security measures are crucial for production deployments. From authentication and authorization to data protection and server hardening, every layer of your application stack requires careful attention to security details.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Clean Code Laravel: Project Structure and Design Patterns Guide</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/clean-code-laravel-project-structure.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 09:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/clean-code-laravel-project-structure.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Writing clean, maintainable code in Laravel applications requires more than just understanding the framework&amp;rsquo;s features. It demands a systematic approach to organizing your project structure, implementing proven design patterns, and following established best practices that make your codebase scalable and readable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laravel provides excellent flexibility, but this freedom can sometimes lead to messy codebases if developers don&amp;rsquo;t establish clear conventions early on. This comprehensive guide will walk you through proven strategies for creating professional Laravel applications that are easy to maintain, test, and scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Advanced Laravel Debugging with Logs: Production Issues Troubleshooting</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/advanced-laravel-debugging-with-logs.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/advanced-laravel-debugging-with-logs.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When your Laravel application starts acting up in production, proper logging becomes your lifeline. Unlike development environments where you can use tools like dd() or dump(), production debugging requires a more sophisticated approach. This comprehensive guide walks you through advanced Laravel debugging techniques using logs that will help you identify, track, and resolve production issues efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-laravels-logging-architecture"&gt;Understanding Laravel&amp;rsquo;s Logging Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laravel provides a robust logging system built on top of the Monolog library. The framework offers multiple logging channels, each designed for specific use cases. Before diving into advanced debugging techniques, you need to understand how Laravel handles logging under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Deploy Laravel Application to VPS with Nginx: Complete Production Guide</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/deploy-laravel-to-vps-with-nginx-complete-guide.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 09:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/deploy-laravel-to-vps-with-nginx-complete-guide.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Deploying a Laravel application to a VPS (Virtual Private Server) with Nginx gives you complete control over your hosting environment and superior performance compared to shared hosting. This comprehensive guide will walk you through the entire process, from server setup to production optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-youll-learn"&gt;What You&amp;rsquo;ll Learn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up a VPS for Laravel deployment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure Nginx for optimal Laravel performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secure your application with SSL certificates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implement production best practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up automated deployments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor and maintain your application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="prerequisites"&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting, ensure you have:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>5 Laravel extensions that you must install on your Visual Studio Code</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2024/04/5-laravel-extensions-that-you-must-install-on-your-visual-studio-code.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 21:23:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2024/04/5-laravel-extensions-that-you-must-install-on-your-visual-studio-code.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re just getting started with Laravel or even if you&amp;rsquo;ve been working with it for a while, using the right tools can make a big difference. Visual Studio Code (VS Code) is one of the most popular code editors among web developers, and thankfully, it has a great ecosystem of extensions that can help boost your productivity when working with Laravel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll go through five essential VS Code extensions that you should install if you&amp;rsquo;re working with Laravel. These tools will help you write code faster, reduce bugs, and improve your workflow overall.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Belajar Membuat Aplikasi Pertama Anda dengan Laravel</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2024/04/belajar-membuat-aplikasi-pertama-anda-dengan-laravel.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 15:58:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2024/04/belajar-membuat-aplikasi-pertama-anda-dengan-laravel.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ketika kita pertama kali melangkah ke dalam dunia pengembangan web, rasanya seperti memasuki sebuah labirin yang penuh dengan kode dan logika yang rumit. Namun, ada sesuatu yang menarik tentang proses belajar bagaimana segala sesuatu terhubung dan bekerja bersama untuk membentuk sebuah aplikasi web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apakah Anda sedang mencari hobi baru atau ingin mengejar karier sebagai pengembang web, membangun aplikasi pertama Anda adalah pengalaman yang sangat berharga. Dengan memahami dasar-dasar pengembangan web, Anda akan memiliki dasar yang kuat untuk mempelajari teknologi-teknologi baru dan membangun aplikasi yang lebih kompleks di masa depan.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>how to install and configure yajra datatable in Laravel</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2023/08/how-to-install-and-configure-yajra.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2023 00:13:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2023/08/how-to-install-and-configure-yajra.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the realm of modern web development, providing a seamless user experience and enhancing the overall performance of your web applications is paramount. One essential aspect that plays a pivotal role in achieving these goals is efficient data presentation and manipulation. This is where Yajra DataTables comes into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yajra DataTables is a powerful and versatile jQuery-based plugin for Laravel, designed to simplify the process of displaying data in tabular form with advanced features such as filtering, sorting, pagination, and more. It empowers developers to create interactive and dynamic data tables effortlessly, significantly improving how data is showcased to end users.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Cara Menjalankan Project Laravel Clone dari GitHub</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2023/04/cara-menjalankan-project-laravel-clone.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 23:08:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2023/04/cara-menjalankan-project-laravel-clone.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sebelum kita melakukan cloning project Laravel dari GitHub, pastikan kamu telah menginstal tools berikut agar proses berjalan lancar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools di bawah ini sangat penting. Tanpa keduanya, kamu tidak akan bisa menjalankan project Laravel dengan benar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer"&gt;
 Git
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://getcomposer.org/download/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer"&gt;
 Composer
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Untuk mendapatkan project Laravel dari GitHub, ada dua cara:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Menggunakan Git&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mengunduh via file ZIP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tidak ada perbedaan signifikan, hanya beda cara ambilnya. Kita bahas dua-duanya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-cara-clone-menggunakan-git"&gt;💻 Cara Clone Menggunakan Git&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salin URL repository dari GitHub (HTTPS atau SSH).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>