<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tutorial on Buana Coding</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/tutorial/</link><description>Recent content in Tutorial on Buana Coding</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.buanacoding.com/tags/tutorial/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to Implement OAuth2 in Go Google GitHub and Facebook Login</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-implement-oauth2-in-go-google-github-facebook-login.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-implement-oauth2-in-go-google-github-facebook-login.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants to create yet another account with yet another password. I&amp;rsquo;ve built authentication systems that required users to sign up with email and password, and the drop-off rate was painful. Then I added &amp;ldquo;Login with Google&amp;rdquo; and conversions jumped 40%. Users already have accounts they trust - why make them create new ones?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OAuth2 lets users authenticate with providers they already use - Google, GitHub, Facebook, whatever. You get verified emails, users don&amp;rsquo;t manage more passwords, and everyone&amp;rsquo;s happy. The best part? It&amp;rsquo;s not as complicated as it looks once you understand the flow.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Upload Files to AWS S3 in Go Complete Guide with SDK v2</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-upload-files-to-aws-s3-in-go-with-sdk-v2.html</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/10/how-to-upload-files-to-aws-s3-in-go-with-sdk-v2.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve built any real application, you know file storage becomes a problem fast. User avatars, document uploads, video files - they pile up quickly, and you need somewhere reliable to put them. That&amp;rsquo;s where AWS S3 comes in. It&amp;rsquo;s like having unlimited storage that you only pay for what you use, and it integrates beautifully with Go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS recently rewrote their entire Go SDK with v2, and honestly, it&amp;rsquo;s a massive improvement. Cleaner APIs, better error handling, proper context support - everything you&amp;rsquo;d want in a modern Go library. If you&amp;rsquo;re starting fresh or thinking about upgrading from v1, this guide has you covered.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Laravel API Authentication with Sanctum Complete Tutorial 2025</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-api-authentication-sanctum-2025.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/laravel-api-authentication-sanctum-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Laravel Sanctum offers two simple authentication modes that cover most applications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cookie-based auth for SPAs that live on the same top-level domain as your backend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal access tokens for mobile apps, third‑party clients, or server‑to‑server use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial walks through both flows end‑to‑end, including the necessary configuration (CORS, cookies, stateful domains), how to issue and revoke tokens, how to protect routes, and how to test the result. You’ll also find production notes to avoid common pitfalls.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Computer Vision with OpenCV Complete Guide to Object Detection and Face Recognition in Python</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/computer-vision-opencv-object-detection-face-recognition-tutorial.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/09/computer-vision-opencv-object-detection-face-recognition-tutorial.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered how your phone instantly recognizes your face to unlock, or how Tesla&amp;rsquo;s autopilot spots other cars on the highway? That&amp;rsquo;s computer vision at work, and honestly, it&amp;rsquo;s not as complicated as it looks. When I first managed to get a webcam to detect my face in real-time, I was blown away. It felt like I&amp;rsquo;d just taught my computer to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crazy thing is, you can build this stuff yourself. No PhD required, no expensive equipment - just Python, OpenCV, and some patience. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with computer vision for a few years now, and I still get excited every time I see a detection algorithm actually work on messy, real-world data.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Essential Linux Commands Every Developer Must Know in 2025</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/essential-linux-commands-every-developer-must-know-2025.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Aug 2025 10:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/essential-linux-commands-every-developer-must-know-2025.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;rsquo;re building web applications, managing servers, or working in DevOps, mastering Linux commands is absolutely essential for any developer in 2025. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with Linux systems for years, and I can tell you that knowing the right commands at the right time can save you hours of work and make you incredibly productive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux dominates the server world, powers most cloud infrastructure, and is the backbone of modern development environments. From managing &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/install-docker-on-ubuntu-24-04-with-compose-v2-and-rootless.html"&gt;
 Docker containers
&lt;/a&gt;
 to setting up &lt;a href="https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/nginx-certbot-ubuntu-24-04-free-https.html"&gt;
 secure web servers with HTTPS
&lt;/a&gt;
, these commands will be your daily companions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>gRPC in Go Complete Guide from Basics to Production Ready Services</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/grpc-in-go-complete-guide-from-basics-to-production.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/grpc-in-go-complete-guide-from-basics-to-production.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building modern distributed systems is tricky business - you need services that can talk to each other quickly and reliably. That&amp;rsquo;s where gRPC comes in and absolutely crushes it. I&amp;rsquo;ve been building REST APIs for years, but when I first tried gRPC, it was like switching from a bicycle to a sports car. The speed difference is insane, plus you get type safety and can use it with practically any programming language.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>FastAPI Tutorial Build REST API from Scratch (Beginner Guide)</title><link>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/fastapi-tutorial-build-rest-api-from-scratch-beginner-guide.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 07:00:00 +0700</pubDate><guid>https://www.buanacoding.com/2025/08/fastapi-tutorial-build-rest-api-from-scratch-beginner-guide.html</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building APIs used to scare me when I first started programming. There&amp;rsquo;s so much to learn - databases, HTTP methods, authentication, error handling. But FastAPI changed everything for me. It&amp;rsquo;s like having training wheels that actually make you faster, not slower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to build a real Book Library API from the ground up. No fluff, no complicated setups - just practical, working code that you can understand and expand on. By the end of this guide, you&amp;rsquo;ll have a fully functional REST API that can handle creating, reading, updating, and deleting books.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>